

▼r.verdecchia@vu.nl | ★ robertoverdecchia.github.io | ☑ robertoverdecchia

Summary_

Research Associate of Software Engineering at the Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU).

Member of the Netherlands Research School for Information and Kwnoledge Systems (SIKS).

Fascinated by empirical software engineering, especially when applied in the fields of software architecture, technical debt, software testing, and software energy efficiency.

Work Experience ____

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

Amsterdam, The Netherlands

2020 - Present RESEARCH ASSOCIATE

- Research Associate in Software Engineering, focusing on Software Architecture and Technical Debt
- · Responsibilities: Carry out.

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam

Amsterdam, The Netherlands

TEACHING ASSISTANT

2015 - Present

- · Courses: Software Testing, Software Architecture, Service Oriented Design, Software Modeling, Service Science
- · Responsibilities: Supervise B.Sc/M.Sc Theses, and research projects. Conduct lectures, seminars and exercise sessions. Tutor teams of students. Review exams and deliverables. Manage e-learning platforms. Attend weekly meetings with instructors to align course content.

KPMG Amsterdam, The Netherlands

GRADUATE RESEARCH INTERN

Apr. 2016 - Oct. 2016

- Graduate research intern focusing on the analysis of software products
- Responsibilities: Architecture reconstruction. Static and dynamic analysis of code bases. Server management. Performance testing. Automation scripting. Statistical data analysis

OMALA Amsterdam, The Netherlands

SOFTWARE ENGINEERING INTERN

Jun. 2015 - Aug. 2015

- · Software engineering intern focusing on the analysis of a large scale heterogeneous system of systems
- Responsibilities: Requirements engineering and architecture trade-off analysis for the Airport Garden City IT infrastructure project of the Lelystad Airport business park

Education

L'Aquila, Italy Amsterdam, The

Gran Sasso Science Institute(GSSI) & Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU)

Netherlands

• Dissertation title: "Identification and Management of Architectural Technical Debt"

Nov. 2016 - Present

Vrije Universiteit Amsterdam (VU)

DOUBLE PH.D. CANDIDATE IN SOFTWARE ENGINEERING

M.Sc. in Computer Science: Software Engineering curriculum

Amsterdam, The Netherlands

• Thesis title: "Static and Dynamic Analysis of Software Energy Efficiency in Industry" (Cum Laude distinction)

University of Florence - School of Engineering (UniFi)

Florence, Italy

2014 - 2016

B.Eng. in Computer Engineering

2011 - 2014

• Thesis title: "Algorithm for Weather-based Naval Routing as an N-stage Decisional Process"

Selected Honors & Awards

2019	Facebook Testing and Verification Award, Facebook Testing and Verification Symposium 2019	Montreal, Canada
	ACM-SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award, IEEE-ACM International Conference on Software	
2019	Engineering (ICSE)	Montreal, Canada

Paper: Scalable Approaches for Test Suite Reduction

Seattle, U.S.A Best Early Career Researcher Award, IEEE International Conference on Software Architecture (ICSA)

Best Paper Award, Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS) 2019

Hawaii, U.S.A

Paper: DecidArch: Playing Cards as Software Architects

2018

Selected Visitings

Electrical and Computer Engineering Department (University of British Columbia)

Vancouver, Canada April 2019 - June 2019

VISITING RESEARCH SCHOLAR

- Topic: Architectural technical debt
- Host: Philippe Kruchten

SEDC Lab, ISTI-CNR (Italian National Research Council)

Pisa, Italy

July 2019

VISITING RESEARCH SCHOLAR

• Topic: Fast static approaches for test flakiness prediction

• Host: Antonia Bertolino

Services_

Program Committee member TechDebt (2021), ICSE (2021), ICSOFT (2021), TechDebt (2020), SOFTENG (2020), GREEN (2019)

Journal Reviewer JSS (2019-), EMSE (2020-), IST (2020-), SUSCOM (2019-)

Ogranizing Commitee BoKSS (2021, Virtualization Chair)

ICSE (2018, 2019), ICSA (2018, 2019), ECSA (2018, 2019), MOBILESoft (2018, 2019), **External Conference Reviewer**

ESEC/FSE (2018), ICT4S (2018, 2019)

Student Volunteer ICSE (2018, 2019), ICPE (2018)

Selected Publications

• R. Verdecchia, P. Kruchten, P. Lago, I. Malavolta. Building and evaluating a theory of architectural technical debt in software-intensive systems. Journal of Software and Systems (JSS), 2021.

- R. Verdecchia, P.Lago, I. Malavolta, P. Lago, I.Ozkaya. ATDx: Building an Architectural Technical Debt Index. International Conference on Evaluation of Novel Approaches to Software Engineering (ENASE), 2020.
- R. Verdecchia, P.Kruchten, P. Lago. Architectural Technical Debt: A Grounded Theory. European Conference on Software Architecture (ECSA),
- R. Verdecchia, I. Malavolta, and P. Lago. Guidelines for Architecting Android Apps: A mixed-method Empirical Study. International Conference on Software Architecture (ICSA), 2019.
- E. Cruciani, B. Miranda, R. Verdecchia, A. Bertolino. Scalable Approaches for Test Suite Reduction. International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2019. TACM SIGSOFT Distinguished Paper Award.
- P. Lago, Jia F. Cai, Remco C. de Boer, Philippe Kruchten, and R. Verdecchia. DecidArch: Playing Cards as Software Architects. Hawaii International Conference on System Sciences (HICSS), 2019. P Best Paper Award. ISSIP-IBM-CBA Student Paper Award for Best Industry Studies Paper.
- I. Malavolta, R. Verdecchia, M. Bruntink, B. Filipovic and P. Lago. On the Evolution of Maintainability Issues of Android Applications IEEE International Conference on Software Maintenance and Evolution (ICSME), 2018.
- R. Verdecchia, R. A. Saez, Giuseppe Procaccianti, and P. Lago. Empirical Evaluation of the Energy Impact of Refactoring Code Smells. International Conference on ICT for Sustainability (ICT4S), 2018. P Runner-up Best Paper Award.
- B. Miranda, E. Cruciani, R. Verdecchia, A. Bertolino. FAST Approaches to Scalable Similarity-based Test Case Prioritization. International Conference on Software Engineering (ICSE), 2018.
- R. Verdecchia. Identifying Architectural Technical Debt in Android Applications through Compliance Checking. International Conference on Mobile Software Engineering and Systems (MobileSoft), 2018. The Bronze medal - ACM Student Research Competition.
- R. Verdecchia, Giuseppe Procaccianti, I. Malavolta, P. Lago, and J. Koedijk. Estimating Energy Impact of Software Releases and Deployment Strategies: The KPMG Case Study. Empirical Software Engineering and Measurement (ESEM), 2017.

Skills_

Databases

Frameworks/tools

Programming Python, R, Bash, C++, Java, GO, Scala MySQL, MongoDB, Cassandra Selenium, JMeter, Android, Kafka, Spark, Docker, GCP, Jenkins

Typesetting LaTeX **Version Control** Git, SVN

Italian (native), German (native), English, Dutch, Spanish Languages